[Music]
hello good morning good evening
everybody i hope you're all doing well
welcome to ask abidjit 87
as you know today is a live video chat
session so i'm going to take video
questions from those of you who will who
would like to come on the video chat
so let us let me share the link for so
that you guys can join the video chat
let me share it
and pin it on the chat one question per
person as always
let me put that up where is it where is
it where is it where is it
uh here it is let me pin the message
and now you should be able to enter the
video chat
if you can see the pinned message and i
hope you're all well i can see people
are already coming in it's it's great to
it's great to see
everybody who is coming in
uh so before we begin uh let us take a
moment to pay tribute to one of india's
greatest sons chatrapati shivaji maharaj
today is his birth anniversary his
jayanti
one of india's greatest sons of all time
definitely one of the greatest kings of
india in the past one thousand years
after the great uh raja raja raj in
rajinder chula i would say that he was
the greatest
so uh
so i would like to pay tribute to the
great sun of our soil and let us also
uh if we wish to honor the memory and
the legacy of chatrapati shivaji
maharaja we should also ask ourselves
what were his principles what were his
values if you guys know me you would
know that i have said that the great
conqueror ching is khan was a man of
principles well i can also say that
chatripathy maharaja himself was a great
man of principles he lived and died by a
set of values and principles
it's not enough to shout slogans and
feel happy
we if we really wish to honor the great
man we should
try try and study and understand his
principles and we should ask ourselves
what was his vision for india
if he were if he were to see india today
would he be happy to see what we have
made of it
i i strongly suspect that if the
chatrapati shivaji maharaja were to see
india
the way it is today he would we would be
very disappointed with what our
so-called leaders have done since 1947.
so if we truly wish to honor him
we need to live by his principles and
try and take india back to where he
wanted it to be in the viswara
the the
secular social
socialist republic of india is not the
hinduish he wanted to establish
and i know that vr
maharaja is one is a one in a thousand
kind of person but if
us we have even one percent or two
percent of his strength and greatness if
we stick together band together work
together we can do it so let us try and
honor the great man by living according
to his values and principles
okay
uh enough of that
uh let's try and bring in some people uh
whom shall i bring in let me bring in
shambhavi first
hello good evening
good evening
yes where are you from ma'am
i'm from kolkata
great to see you great to see you
shambhavi what's your question
so uh my question is that the mughal
king akbar said to make an intelligent
use of secularism in the state club so
was this political interest generally
like that or was he getting a social
security from that
i could not get half of your question
i'm very sorry i think it was not clear
could you please repeat a little slowly
perhaps
sure sure sir i was saying that the
mughal king akbar is said to make an
intelligent uh use of secularism in his
statecraft so was his political interest
genuinely like that or was he getting
any kind of social security from that
okay okay the guy what's his name akbar
in secularism yes our textbooks our
historians have tried very very
hard to portray akbar as a very secular
and just king a very benevolent king we
just need to look at a couple of
incidents from his life to understand
what sort of person he was he besieged
the city of chittorgarh
he was eventually after after a
prolonged siege able to take over the
city
the rajputs who were defending the city
were massacred their women
committed johar and then there were a
lot of people who had surrendered and
what this individual did is in one day
he beheaded 30 000 men women children
akbar
so is that the mark of secularism we
have to ask ourselves that's all i need
to tell you i think we are all
intelligent enough to see that if a
person has done such a thing
and that is not the only incident by the
way there are lots of other incidents
such as this not of that extreme
magnitude but along the same lines that
you can find from the historical record
from the chroniclers of the time that he
has done so i don't see anything secular
or benevolent about akbar he has been
portrayed that way by historians for
various reasons but he's not that please
please understand and you can look it up
yourself all the information is out
there in the public domain just look it
up it's there it's not i'm not making it
up it's part of the historical right
right
okay
thank you nice question
nice meeting you bye
okay let's bring in somebody else uh who
else do we have let's bring in somebody
new i haven't seen before
uh let's bring in mr shreesh
hello
hello sir
sir nice meeting you once again
yes sir so sir sir actually my question
was um so sir i wanted to ask the origin
of indian classical music sarah i myself
um sir i'm very much fascinated by our
indian classical music so sir answer
the second part of the question is sir
what steps should be taken by our
country
to
develop a taste
to develop taste for
to
develop the taste of indian classical
music among the youth of our country
very
very good question
so if you
if you look at various historical texts
and if you look at various
college and university syllabuses there
is absolutely nothing in the history
departments about indian classical music
i have not seen anything anymore the
historians have not done any research
into the origins of indian classical
music how old is this tradition etc uh
there was this uh
about more than a hundred years ago
there was this great uh
uh
music historian i would say his name was
pandit bhatt kande i think he he
studied the raga's various indian
classical ragas ragazi classified and
organized them into various thoughts and
all that that's the only that's the last
proper work that's in that's been done
but if you look at the uh
the enormous
corpus of the various ragas etc that we
have it's very clear that this is a very
ancient system it's been developed over
god knows how many centuries
every raga has evolved over the
centuries in the past it was different
today it's different so i don't have an
unfortunately an answer as to how old
this tradition is i would you know
if you ask me to make an educated guess
i would say it would date back to the
vedic times indian classical music must
have started around that time itself
because that that period itself was a
very advanced phase of civilization so
that's what i can say now what can we do
to bring the taste back i mean i mean to
make it more popular among the people
we have to get rid of i mean i would not
say get rid of but we have to reform
bollywood bollywood today does not
propagate what is known what is indian
culture what bollywood presents to
people is something different it's not
indian culture it does not represent
indian culture it is not representative
of indian culture it's trying to uh
it's trying to it's trying to engineer
the indian taste for music
to to attune it to certain foreign kinds
of music so what needs to happen is
from the grassroots if you can if you
can
if you can promote
musicians who are interested in this i
mean there are lots of folk musicians in
rajasthan in every state actually and
there are lots of classical musicians
also but they don't get any exposure
they get no uh
yeah they get no exposure at all so yes
sir if you have a bollywood song you
will find it blasted everywhere there is
so much promotion there are there's so
much money behind it and when it comes
to folk musicians
musicians who are let's say playing
sitar or vocalists you get no exposure
just somehow this needs to change i
think as indian society gets more
prosperous all of this will get more
exposure but perhaps by the time it may
be too late because we we no longer have
the great musicians of your you know so
something needs to be done i would say
the government of india it has a
ministry of culture
yes i think it is the job of the
ministry of culture to promote indian
culture i think it is one of the least
performing ministries the worst
performing ministries in the government
of india so that need they need to wake
up
and something needs to be done but it is
it is uh certainly very important that
we revive indian classical music so it's
a very good question that you've asked
thank you sir thank you so much sir
bye sir all right thank you great
question thank you
okay whom shall we bring in
my problem is i don't recognize people's
faces
and then
okay let me bring in mr nirmith
i'm great as always yes sir what's your
question nice to meet you sir uh i
wanted to ask that who was the last
greatest man in the leader because our
current leader is not having that much
influence in the southern states
and what it takes to
be like that means
it cannot be from one geography or one
language or even a ethnicity like
anything
yes who was their last great uh pan
india leader
so i would say you if you if you look at
the last time india was politically
unified under a non-foreign constitution
non-foreign nonsense thing it was under
the maratha empire around the mid 1750s
so whoever was the peshwa at the time
that person was the last pan india
leader now that peshwa was essentially i
don't remember who it was i we can look
it up of course it was around 1759 or so
that we had the greatest extent of the
maratha empire from southern ghandar
afghanistan all the way to
most of southern india
so this empire was built over a long
time it's genesis lies in the greatness
of chattaroo he did the hard work he put
the framework in place that his
successors were able to exploit and
benefit from to create this uh
this empire so it was not a one person
thing it was it was the work of multiple
generations of leaders the last great
great pan-india leader was uh
who could i say it was most likely it
was
i i think
rajendra cholla conquered parts of
northern india up to up to varanasi etc
he conquered the ganga valley and all
and
but he did not go all the way north
i would say the last greatest leader
before the last peshwa who was in charge
of that must have been
skandagupta most likely because he
conquered all of india and unified all
of india under one dominion skanda gupta
was about 1500 years ago
and of course we had lalitha mukhta also
who conquered very large parts of india
and way beyond that so we have a few
very notable leaders who conquered so
much and unified the country it's
happened from time to time i think it is
time for that to happen again
unfortunately we have a prime minister
et cetera but because of the structure
of the indian government the
constitution and all the other so-called
checks and balances etc the
prime minister of india does not have
that much power as we think he has
so things need to change for india to
become great again but let's see let's
see how it goes right
sir
at least ahead of others
unfortunately lost it is not his fault
but he was also great but not i see the
duty of a leader is to win that is
non-negotiable so that's just how it
goes
all right sir
good question thank you very much thanks
bye
okay whom shall i bring in
uh
let me bring in mr khushal
hello
hello sir
so my question is hi sir
where are you from
hyderabad i was in the last uh live
session
oh you were there my question all right
yes
so my question is uh what can we do
about the naga subreddit sir like what's
the update what's going on there right
now like i've been trying to get update
but
i can't find any article like what do
you think what's going on there right
now
yeah even i don't have sufficient
information uh the the part of india is
rather remote and there is not much news
that comes out of the place so we don't
quite know what's happening i think the
situation is more or less reasonably
under some kind of control i don't have
clarity unfortunately that is a
sensitive part of india and
for whatever reason maybe for good
reasons a lot of news does not come out
from there
so unfortunately unless you are a
military uh you're part of the indian
military unless you have boots on the
ground there human we may not be able to
quite know what's happening there
so
you know because i don't have sufficient
information i cannot tell you what
exactly the situation there what i can
say from a big picture perspective is
that the whole of india needs to be
properly integrated together like the
for instance the northeast of india has
been given this step motherly treatment
for decades from 1947 onwards it was
constantly kept under developed
deliberately so all of that needs to be
undone we need to integrate this part
this part of india with what what is
called the so-called mainstream india we
need connectivity good connectivity uh
airports we need railways we need roads
all that hopefully connectivity wise by
sea also if you can engineer that sort
of a geographical
marvel
so that's what needs to happen the place
needs to be developed there should be
infrastructure we need to we need to
have job opportunities hospitals schools
colleges universities if you develop all
that there will be no incidency
development is the only answer
development is on the only answer
absolutely
okay sir thank you so much sir yes thank
you good question thank you nice meeting
you thank you sir
yeah bye
okay whom shall we bring in
my good friend is there i'll make him
wait just a little bit more uh
uh whom shall we bring in i get the
feeling it's the same four five people
who are coming in every time let's bring
in mr dhruv
hello
hello sir
hi
sir
where are you from
i'm from delhi delhi very nice sir
so my question is as i've observed sir
that's a uh
vedic india was more acceptable to
homosexuality and so sexual education as
we can see sir in various temples there
are many erotic sculptures and sir as we
can see in mahabharata also there is a
character named shigandi who was also
homosexual sir so sir what changed that
uh
this thing become
this thing uh was is now seen in a very
negative way so
yeah good question so first of all uh
let me uh just issue a small correction
shaken was not homosexual she candy was
a
transgender transgender that sort of
person it was not a homosexual person it
was a person who was who had ambiguous
uh gender
maybe some somewhere between male and
female so the thing is this
there has you know the leftists the
professors the historians they have they
we know how much they hate hinduism
indian culture and even despite that
they have not been able to find a single
instance of any sort of discrimination
against uh homosexuality or lgbtq
whatever they call it these days
not even a single instance in indian
history right it tells you that indian
society has been always very open nobody
cared what what your sexual orientation
what your gender what gender fluidity
whatever it was no one ever cared and
there was no taboo against
whatever any of these things and like
you say we have these cultures on
temples that which show how open and
free indian society was so what happened
we came under foreign occupation in the
past 1000 years the abrahamic culture is
very different from indian culture what
we call what we have the kind of culture
we had in india for thousands of years
it's still visible to some extent in to
the east of india places like uh
southeast asia thailand burma myanmar
etc if you see their culture they are
far more open
and uh liberal
in the true sense of the word liberal
than what india is today right so
because we were under 1 000 years of
foreign occupation brutal foreign
occupation that's why women had to start
covering up their bodies people had to
start behaving in a very different way
than what the culture says and that's
why all these regressive
backward patriarchal attitudes crept
into indian society over 1000 years
first it was the turks and then it was
the british and portuguese and other
foreign occupiers and their morality was
always the same it's it's the abrahamic
morality whether you like it or not and
the so that's how it was so that's why
the attitudes have changed what we may
no longer be under foreign occupation
technically today but it takes time for
a 1 000 years of occupation that
mentality that siege mentality to go
away and all of that has become part of
society just for the sake of survival
and that's why we we have this these
attitudes that are prevalent in india
today so it's because of the foreign
occupation not because of indian culture
thank you sir
thank you nice question
nice to meet you
thank you
okay let's bring in
whom shall i bring in people are coming
and going
let's bring in mr aryan
hello
have you been on this show before
no i've not been here before okay okay
great great nice meeting you sir what's
your question yes thank you so my
question is do you think that there
should be regulations put on the media
as you can see how influential it is and
how it influences elections in countries
like the us
yes excellent question so
i would say that there needs to be some
regulation in the media in the sense
that
we should not allow foreign funding
in media organizations in the agencies
when you have foreign funding it is
foreign interference because whoever is
giving you the money you will have to do
what they want right otherwise the
source of your funding is cut off and
then you no longer have a media
organization
so i am not saying every single news
outlet in india is controlled by or
funded by foreign organizations but
there are certainly many and you can
just follow the money it's quite it's
not hard to find so many of these news
organizations agencies outlets are
funded not all but there are certainly
some that we know of there are funded
there may be more that are funded from
abroad and they get lots of funding from
abroad and when you have that big source
of funding you want to protect it you
want to keep benefiting from that and
that's why you are forced to give a
certain flavor to your news that your
masters want
so we need to ensure there is no foreign
funding in the media
we have plenty of money in the country
india is no longer a very poor country
there's plenty of money investment
capital etc available we need to cut cut
off the foreign funding not just in
india i i would say that all countries
in the world should have this law that
foreign funding is not allowed in the
media because that will bring in foreign
interference and then you have all the
manipulation of the opinions and
interference in elections because the
media is
very influential when it comes to
elections the kind of projections they
put across and so many things so i would
say that that is one thing that needs to
be done and
secondly i am i am not in favor of
censorship i think everybody should be
allowed to express their opinion freely
but as long as it is a genuine opinion
as long as they are not trying to uh
engineer
certain kinds of perceptions or because
they are taking money from somebody so
that's the kind of thing that's need to
be there i think we need to have a free
and fair media but the media that is
funded from abroad is not free and fair
so that's what i would suggest if we can
do that that will take away 95 of the
problems
right so do you think so that u.s media
is funded by china
uh i have not looked into it but uh
maybe maybe you can look into it and let
us let us know what do you say
thank you
all right nice meeting you sir
okay
mr aditya
hello hello sir hello pleased to meet
you hi nice to meet you where are you
from sir
i'm from bengaluru karnataka
nice to meet you what's your question
sir
so i'm just going to ask two questions
you can answer whichever you want
no problem thank you okay so the first
question is
sir
in
in all of indian history what has the
role of jainism been
that's the first question
and the second question is sir when you
want to achieve a goal
should you do you think we should uh
give up on principles to do do that or
should we give up on the goal and change
a goal if
that
takes us to like keep our principles
that's a very good question i will take
the second question uh i am not a
very
big expert of jainism so i think i will
pass on that one but i will take up the
second question so let's say you have a
big objective
let's say let's take the the example of
chatrapati shivaji maharaj he was born
into an india that was occupied by the
turks india was occupied brute and there
was this brutal operation of of hindus
of indians of indian culture destruction
and all that that's the india he was
born into he wanted to achieve
freedom from the turks
now
he was born
he was the son of a small chieftain who
was serving the i think the adil shah's
was it most likely yes
so that is the situation he was born
into now he wanted to achieve that so he
waged this guerrilla work what is now
called guerrilla warfare which means
that you don't meet your enemy in open
battle
you
hide wherever you can you try to cut
them bleed them and then run away that
sort of thing which is what the rajputs
would never do the rajputs believed it
that sort of thing right we'll we'll
fight with honor we'll come from the
front we'll we'll challenge you and
we'll show our bravery even if we lose
that's the kind of attitude the rajputs
had the marathas were very different
their objective was to win they didn't
care how they won as long as they
defeated the turks
and the thing is this the turks were
perpetrating brutal inhuman
oppression on the people of india it
doesn't matter how you defeat such
barbarians you have to defeat them even
if you cheat even if you lie even if you
steal you have to get rid of them from
the country the long-term prosperity and
security of the country is the overall
objective however you achieve it doesn't
matter as long as as long as you keep
serving the people of the country you
can take any root any method any path
to achieve that so the principle is the
principles the principles were never
broken the principle is my my job is to
serve the people of india
my job is to serve them serve dharma and
my job is to free my principle and my
objective is to free india and how to
achieve it doesn't matter sometimes i'll
make a compromise with them sometimes i
will sign an agreement with them and
give up some forts
later on i'll take it back when the time
is right
so you need to have a set of principles
that you will not deviate from apart
from that you can break the rules as
long as the larger objective is met that
is the that is the uh the way
the these are the teachings of vishnu
i would say that shivaji lived by that
uh the later bharatas who were able to
reconquer india also lived by that and
even kings like uh
skanda gupta samudra gupta
and the cholas et cetera they also live
by the principles of vishnu
so as long as you understand that you
can
you you're fine you're not you're not
doing anything wrong
okay thank you sir
thank you
thank you thank you so much nice meeting
you thank you bye bye
okay let us uh
let's bring in mr udd
hello hello sir how are you sir oh we
have met before haven't you yes sir i
have i've been here i've been there all
the sessions so
all the sessions
where are you from again
saudi arabia sir saudi arabia all right
what's your question sir so
my question is like i don't know the
exact thing behind it or what was the
reason i want to know the reason
we keep on seeing the example of the
trojan horse right like the greeks
wanted to enter troy so so what made
them hide their people into the horse
like into the wooden horse and then make
them do that
so like what's the history like what
made them do it do you know anything
about it
see in warfare the warfare is won and
lost through deception
yes right so we had this war going on
the trojan war and it was at a stalemate
kind of situation none of the sides was
winning we had one side which was
entrenched in this walled city and you
had another side that was besieging the
city and you had reached this state of
equilibrium equilibrium neither was able
to make a breakthrough it went on for
years i think
so these guys they came up with a new
idea let's try something different
something different to deceive the
opponent all warfare is based on
deception that's what sunju said so
there is an example of
that itself the principle of deception
so i think it's a question of thinking
differently lateral thinking think after
outside the box think inside the trojan
wars whatever you want to call it and
that's that's how this thing happened i
maybe it's a real historical incident we
don't quite know but it's a very famous
story and a great example of deception
and warfare
yes sir thank you sir all right so if i
could just ask like within that question
only i'm not adding another one i just
wanted you i just want to know
yes sir so was it a war which made them
go do that
a previous war which they were not able
to win
it was the trojan war
so the greeks were not able to win that
and then they had to do this
yes okay sir thank you sir thanks a lot
sir see you soon sir see you tomorrow
all right all right nice meeting you bye
uh who else
who else
is there somebody i have not seen before
i'm getting the same people every time
i would like to give opportunities to
people i've not met before let's bring
in mr arun i hope it's somebody new
hello
oh hi uh hi vijay nice to meet you again
nice to again all right we have we're
here are we
only once uh i guess there was one uh
yeah question that i had asked about the
you know overall impact okay that's
where i'm from where i'm from uh i'm
based in hong kong yeah hong kong all
right so what's your question
yeah so my question is uh you know there
have been uh you know many years of uh
colonism by the britishers right and all
the commonwealth countries which have
been uh
under their rule uh but till now for all
the damage in all the things that they
have done they're never given us any
reparations until they have given us an
apology
uh and then i do see that a lot of
countries have done it for african
countries uh i mean uh recently also
they have you know some other countries
they have given apology for but till now
they never done it for india and they
have done the biggest damage to indian
uh you know economy and everything
they're looter and all that stuff
yes so i understand that what is it and
how can
even they come to the realization that
they should be apologizing for at least
doing all the ill deeds and also
you know what can we do from our side to
make this uh you know whole thing come
into a bigger light
yes it's a question i've got multiple
times but it's a good question so uh
you know what we don't need an apology
from them
we would want reparations war
reparations from these people
uh the thing is this the reason why they
have not given any reparations any
damages any apology or anything to india
it's because india has always been a
terribly weak
country until now today india is rising
for the first time since 1947.
you had all these decades of the
neherubian rate of growth in which india
was growing at one two percent three
percent per year so india never become
large sizable power from the economic
perspective and if you don't have a
large economy you don't have a large
military so india was always a small
weak nation despite its large size and
nobody respected india because india was
a land of poverty because of the small
economy everybody was starving it was
there whether we like it or not that's
just the way it was
so india never
was able to gain in the the respect of
the west and india was never able to
become so sizable that people would
worry about the consequences of what
they had done in the past even today
india is not in a position to push the
uk around but once india reaches about
10 trillion dollars in its economy
that's when there will be consequences
that the uk will have to face if they
don't uh behave in a certain manner
towards india the kind of difference
that they show towards china today
india is not in a position to command
that so it is see the world doesn't care
about what's right and what's wrong the
world respects power the world fears
power respect comes from fear
so you have to make the world fear you
first then they will respect you and
then they will apologize to you and they
may even issue some reparations or you
may be able to extract reparations from
them so it's all about see that the
world
actually it may look like a very
civilized place
but in from the geopolitical perspective
global perspective is the rule of the
jungle the biggest fish wins so that's
what india has to do and then things
will become very different once we reach
that position
okay sir okay thank you very much
thank you nice meeting you again thank
you bye
okay
uh
do i have somebody new
sorry
nice to meet you you're the first time
here right
yes sir i am the first i'm the first
time here
first nice to meet you
yeah
so my question is is the concept of
communism uh sounds so good on paper
but why uh the country which adopts it
uh usually don't succeed
very good question very good concise
question but a very good question
right communism sounds great on paper
communism says everybody should be equal
right
everybody should have the same amount of
money everybody should have the same
kind of house to live in the same
opportunities everybody everything
should be the same
so it is not about equality of
opportunity it is about equality of
outcome
right they want everybody to be equal
now look at the let's look at the world
around us is the world an equal place is
equality something that is not a part of
nature
look at the different animals that we
have we have lions we have tigers we
have elephants we have little mice we
have little rabbits is the world equal
no the world is not equal look at human
beings some are tall some are short some
are not very intelligent some are super
smart geniuses
the world is not equal when we uh
when we play the olympics are we
celebrating equality or inequality we
have a hundred meter race do we ensure
that everybody ends at the same point
and everybody gets a gold medal no it's
not that we are celebrating inequality
when we play the world cup in quicker
football we want only one team to win
because it's all about who is the best
inequality is the way of nature and we
are trying to go against nature when we
are trying to impose equality of outcome
when we uh
when we go to school does everybody do
does the teacher give everybody first
rank why do we have exams why do we have
job interviews the world is about
inequality everybody should get the same
opportunity
you cannot give people different kinds
of opportunities some people are
oppressed suppressed and some people are
given more opportunity that is wrong
there should be equality of opportunity
and then it's up to you what you make of
the opportunity
in communism they're trying to create
equality of outcome which is just
unnatural it just doesn't work and
secondly communism is a way of it's it's
they say religion as the opium of the
masses actually communism is the opium
of the masses because they make people
feel everybody will be equal but at the
end of the day in every single communist
country where the communist experiment
has been done you will find that there
is this
one stratum of society 99 of people who
are all poor or at the same level and
there is this source very small super
minority who have all the privileges
the communist leadership
so it's always been like that and every
time they make the excuse they did not
do it properly they did not implement
communism properly so let's try it again
in a new country and that's how it goes
so that is the reason why communism has
failed over and over and over again and
it will keep failing every time they're
going to try it
all right sir
so i'm going to add something in the
question so
so may i go ahead
so what is the best form of government
according to you
look at the past 10 000 years look at
the greatest kingdoms empires everything
and see what worked that is the best
form of government
all right thank you sir
thank you nice meeting you good
questions
okay let's bring in mr shorya
hello hello good evening
good evening nice to meet you sir where
are you from
and i am for the second time
okay no problem what's your question sir
so
and coincidentally i'm again wearing the
same t-shirt
so my question is that
like
we see in uh invader is coming to india
like i extend
my question is that how did they talk
like they have totally different
languages if vasco da gama comes to
india then here we speak a different
language and they are totally different
language then how did they communicate
like today we have english as a global
language but
back then
that's a very interesting question that
you asked very interesting question when
these barbaric europeans portuguese
people come to india how did they
communicate
i suspect this is how it happened see
the europeans were in contact with the
arabs we know that
because they got all of india science
knowledge mathematics everything from
the arabic world so many of them knew
arabic so i would expect that when these
sailors like vasco da gama and pirates
etc they would go to other countries and
long voyages they would take experts who
were good at translating languages like
arabic languages that they knew about
right and then when they came to india
india also was in contact with the
arabic world so you would have indian
arabic translators also and that's how
there would be some kind of
communication via a third language so
that's how i think it happened because
india has for thousands of years had
contacts with various other countries
and cultures and the indians would have
known multiple languages especially in
the court of a king
you would have experts who could
translate multiple languages that is a
guarantee
and that's how they would have found
some common language and use that to
communicate
make sense
yes so but i mean
we see this in the whole world like
anyone going to any country in the past
and we see trades happening
so like
uh there must be a common language like
something like that
you talk very specifically about india
my question was like a general thing
like how tad happened if we even had a
different language and no common
language there
see
the world did not begin at a certain
instant when nobody knew each other's
languages right the world has always
been in communication for ind for
instance india and greece
were in contact about two and a half
thousand years ago when the salute when
they when seleucus negative and his
predecessors etc they tried to invade
india and there is there are signa there
are significant similarities between the
languages like the greek and sanskrit so
it is not that hard to communicate and
we would have persian translators also
at that time persian is even closer to
sanskrit than the greek for instance and
india had communication with rome for
for two and a half thousand years so
there was always contact there was
contact with southeast asia for three
thousand i mean three thousand years
before today the
people of kalinga were trading with
southeast asia so it's it's always been
a culture a maritime culture india and
other countries also would be in
communication and contact with
neighboring countries so there's always
this network effect so you'll always
find somebody who can translate
something for you
okay all right sir
thank you nice question nice meeting you
bye
okay
let me bring in
shrey paliwal
all right great nice meeting
you sir actually i've been trying to get
to your stream so i actually have a
i mean quite a
many i would not say many but around
three questions if
if it's possible you can answer them
go ahead ask me i'll i'll take at least
one go ahead
sir my one is related to
uh accu points chakras and martial arts
and how is that
sort of thai martial art in donation
martial arts and
they are able to advance but our indian
martial arts i mean there are still
still lots
of
very used much i mean you can see
used to be many kickboxing league where
many white people used to be rules or
either people used to bring then
suddenly some uh thai people came and
they're
beating the hell out of all the
americans then suddenly sir uh
from filipino a very good boxer his name
was a
manipulation
he just it's just a short guy
and he started beating almost everyone
uh sir
first of all why won't be able to get
this capability of martial from india
many english
being i've seen they said that ones were
finished because
there's too many anime but when i study
and try to contour but and studied that
it was gupta who actually completely
finished their own survival that
some people are saying different and i
mean most of the current historians are
saying different things
okay let's take these two you have taken
two but for you i'm going to make an
exception i'll answer both so i don't
know about chakras and all but yes but
the martial arts
i think india is the place from where
the old and in the olden days martial
are spread out because if you look at
the various martial arts in asia
you have a karate in japan
which essentially originates from
shaolin in china you also have taekwondo
in korea which
seems to have originated from china
again
yes you you have the the uh
you have muay thai in thailand you have
a blood spot in cambodia you have silat
in philippines
in the philippines
in indonesia
both
are from indonesia
from indonesia
no improvement in india i mean we still
have a wrestler
online
what happened is that our tradition our
we had a tradition of martial arts but
it was destroyed systematically by the
foreign occupiers
the turks came to india first and
they did not want the indians to be able
to fight so they systematically bro
destroyed our universities temples all
that and also the martial arts tradition
and the british also did that they
starved india they banned martial arts
you had all these martial arts in india
the rajput martial art of sword fighting
it's it's extinct today and you you had
various other forms of martial arts
all that is left in mainland india is
kalari payutu in south and shasta vidya
which is like two percent of the main
martial art of the world martial art and
we know that india was the home of
martial arts because our great
guru one of our great gurus dharma went
to china and taught them what they now
called kung fu so kung fu came from
india it is a yoga based martial art so
we had these traditions the foreign
occupiers of india destroyed the
traditions
and it is still alive in southeast asia
in china and japan korea etc
now now you say that we have all these
uh wrestlers
but why are we not winning medals it is
because we there is no systematic
teaching
we are we have the genetics we have the
strength subject share strongly submit
genetics
they
400 500 adk
you can look it up so the horns tried to
invade india there were multiple waves
of invasions at the same time they were
also invading
the roman empire
so they were in in
they were spread throughout central asia
and eurasia so they tried invading india
multiple multiple times they took over
gandhar they had kings like kingila and
uh torah mana and what's his name
etc mirakula was a very evil person but
the others were good more or less i mean
reasonably good so they tried invading
into india multiple times it was
skandagupta who repeatedly repulsed
these invasions and he was able to
successfully kick them out of india as
long as he was alive after he died the
invasion started again and the horns
were able to
establish small kingdoms in various
parts of northern india and then they
are simulated within the population
related
but how is it that uh they were able to
finish coons but not islamic invention
also sir i this is what i think sir
because
although india does get under islamic
invasion and
almost all capture gold i mean all india
but will keep many people many kingdoms
still keep fighting so is it that
india effort to still keep fighting
after under islamic islam that islam was
not able to reach china korea and japan
because i actually feel that that is
also a possibility
see the homes were not islamic when they
came to india they were they were they
believe they were believing their their
culture the religion was tangerism it is
the original culture of the
sir holy i was talking about
not the justice islamic and whether i'm
talking about cruelty of both okay okay
got it got it got it so the horns were
not cruel only one of their kings whose
name was
he was cruel he was an atheist the other
hounds they established hindu kingdoms
in in present-day afghanistan they were
called the kabul tries the hindu shahis
they were offending origin and they
defended india from the turkic invaders
in the beginning
you know for a couple of centuries so
the horns were not cruel it is later the
turks who were cruel and they were
barbaric and all that so it's totally
different
tickets are good questions and very nice
meeting you
all right thank you thank you
okay that was a long
interaction
everybody is raising their hand and
waving their hands
rupesh
hello
uh hello good evening sir can you hear
me good evening yes i can hear you where
are you from sir i'm from orange with
maharashtra
all right so what's your question
sir i had actually two questions
uh you can answer any one of them uh the
first question is after independence why
did myanmar nepal sri lanka didn't
become a part of india because actually
they were under british administration
at that time now and even
chandra bose captured that myanmar and
verma while apart so it should have
become a part of india but why didn't it
become a part of india and my second
question is why is like
all countries in which a righteous
government is in power are trying to
expand uh its what we say territory like
india like they are planning for
akandhara like china wants a greater
china russia wants the ussr back turkey
wants its ottoman empire back like kind
of that thing
it has nothing to do with right or left
everybody wants that everybody wants
more power sir that's the nature of
power once you are in power whether your
president prime minister ceo whatever
you want more power that is the simple
nature of power power is a force of
nature
power doesn't like vacuum whether there
is vacuum power will go and expand now
when you have a dearth of power when you
have less power then whoever is under
you will want to get out and they will
want to become independent from you
that's just the nature of uh
of the world so if you look at uh the
history of india in the past 2000 years
we had a great question empire
and then slowly because after kanesha
the kings who succeeded him were not as
powerful then it fragmented because when
you have emperor who is not very
powerful you will not want to pay taxes
to him by took on a why should i pay
taxes to you you're not strong enough so
i'll declare independence that's how it
happens so in 1947 when india became in
the so-called independent india the
indian government was not powerful
enough and they were not even willing to
be able to administer myanmar etc sri
lanka right our leaders wanted to break
they're very very happy to break india
up they were they they gave up east
pakistan which is not bangladesh they
gave up
the indus valley et cetera to the
pakistanis and so on and they even
allowed the pakistanis to take out take
over p okay so india was not powerful
enough our leaders were did not have the
will the willingness
to keep india unified and to fight
against anybody who wants to break india
when you have a leader who has no wish
to keep india unified then why would
countries why would the territories like
myanmar sri lanka want to be part of
that nepal want to be part of that you
are weak you are incompetent you are
going to give this country 30 40 50
years of nairobian rate of growth why
should i be under you let me be
independent i'll manage my own affairs
that's just how it works that's the way
of the world when you have a power when
you have a powerful leader who is able
to give his subjects or her subjects
what they want
everybody wants to be part of that when
you have a weak leader nobody wants to
be part of that
that's just how it goes and that's why
myanmar etc are not part
i think he will have to answer that for
us
why didn't you bring nepal back why
didn't they take back sri lanka come on
i will research on that sir
yeah exactly
all right good question nice meeting you
thank you bye
okay uh let's bring in our great
great one of my favorite guests
hello
yes
important
so it is possible that hindus do eat
horse meat
because
other religion for example
not
naughty not pagan religion
roman religion
in the other religion for example
not religion roman reigns after
sacrificing the
animal for the ritual purposes
the meat of the animal is eaten by the
either the priest or the king or the
people of the community or the people of
the
of that particular region
yes
sacrifice
and from what i can recall right now
after the horse sacrifice was completed
in a ritualistic manner us
just for the purpose of completing the
ritual it doesn't mean that hindus
ancient indians used to eat horse meat
every day nay yes anita it is only for
the purpose of completing this
particular specific ritual that end at
the end of the ashwamedi when the horse
is sacrificed in a ritualistic manner
then everybody eats a little bit of the
meat everybody who the king the queen
the perhaps the the priest perhaps
essa
so i think whoever is interested in this
needs to go to the vedic text
read it properly i think that's what is
mentioned in it if i am mistaken then
please i
forgive me i apologize but that's what i
remember reading
okay so it doesn't mean that hindus used
to eat meat eat eat horse meat every day
i said bilkul binita this is only a very
rare occasion right
but this proves that hindus can eat
horse meat at least
there is nothing in hinduism that says
you cannot eat horse meat or or or goat
meat or rabbit meat
or duck meat or anything
as far as possible don't be cruel the
highest way the best way of living is to
be vegetarian
meat you can eat meat many chutneys etc
in the past used to eat meat
see you know what uh
culture
religion traditions they are not always
logical
we we we need to make sure we need to
understand one thing is my mathematical
logic apply negative
you know culture evolves over centuries
over thousands of years there are lots
of
things that are not remembered today
there are reasons that we don't we may
not be able to re remember today and
things like that and what you're saying
is correct the buffalo
wine animal definitely it's a white
animal
it is like cow but it's black so it is a
relative of
the latin name is it is not the cow it
is a relative of cow but it is different
allah species those are species there so
i think that is the reason why
sacrifice
it is a great sin in all hinduism to do
that but buffalo is a different species
so i think for that reason it is allowed
because
even buffalo meat liquor be hungry
[Music]
okay uh do i see somebody i haven't seen
before is everybody repeated
krishna
hi krishna good evening sir hello
namaste i'm krishna from bangalore
nice meeting you sir nice meeting you
nice very very very glad i got an
opportunity to speak to you sir
so likewise tell me what's your question
uh sir so i'm originally from kerala and
in kerala we have a tradition of
metrolinity so have inherited my family
name from my mother and there is no
system of gold
so uh
do do you have any idea when this
tradition sort of started in kerala or
if it's there in any other any other
part of india
uh unfortunately i don't have the answer
to when and why this started india as
you know
india is a land of lots and lots of
different traditions
we are a very diverse very plural
civilization lots of
diverse traditions whose origins are for
some reason obscure today we have lost
contact with our past
but we are all bound together under one
civilization cultural umbrella so in
kerala like like you say there is this
tradition of matrilineal inheritance and
all that i think there are in kurg also
there is this matrilineal tradition
right the material
in the northeast of india and the garo
hills in meghalaya etc in some places in
the north east you have metro lineal
traditions and customs
so it's not kerala is not the only place
i think in the nyers you have it is it
in the among the nights
yes
and even the satrias as well even the
kings used to
inherit the throne from their uh
metal uncle
right right so it's it's so india has i
mean india has existed for more than 10
000 years as a distinct uh
visible culture and civilization
and so if you look at 10 000 years of
history so much can happen and so many
different traditions can evolve and the
thing about india is that nobody has
ever tried to tell people that you
cannot do this because we do this right
you live your way i respect that i live
my way you respect that and that's how
it's always been so that's why we have
so many diverse traditions coming uh
that have evolved
unfortunately i don't have an answer as
to how this started in kerala maybe i
will look into it it's certainly a
question that's very fascinating it's a
very fascinating tradition
and it's it's a very rare tradition so i
think it should be preserved and it will
be treasured you know with this sort of
tradition in india which which
completely goes against what the
leftists say about this patrilineal
nonsense that they try to uh portray us
as being you know we have all of this we
have so much diversity so i think i will
i'll try and research this maybe i will
call some expert from kerala who can
talk about this perhaps if i can find
somebody but it's very good question i'm
glad you watched it right
that'd be great and then analyzing that
uh what you're doing is uh extremely
amazing sir there are many young young
people who are coming to your show and
then being inspired by what you're doing
so thanks a lot for that sir
thank you so much very nice meeting you
next video
bye-bye
bye bye
okay um gautam panda
hello good evening sir hope you are
good evening
yeah yes so sir my question is that how
is the second space race currently
unfolding and how will the scenario be
like in the future according to you as a
astrophysicist
and
please provide some contrast to first
space race
very interesting question very
interesting question so the first space
race started with the launch of the
sputnik satellite was it 1957 it's
somewhere in the 1950s the americans and
russians were both trying to do this so
what happened is that
uh the americans had this thing called
operation paper clip in which they would
try they were able to abduct or acquire
german rocket scientists
the ones who
was the major fish that they caught so
they brought these people as pow's
prisoners of war de facto to the us and
the russians took whoever else they
could
and these are the scientists who started
the
sergey coroner was russian but the
russians first acquired some german
scientists and they acquired some
expertise like the
r2 rocket was it i don't know what's the
name of the rocket i don't remember
right now but yeah i
too was in icbm and uh sergey korolev
was from ukraine
sergey korolev was the chief designer
they called him the integral yes the
americans called him the integral if you
read the book what's it called
i forget the names of the books man but
yeah so these are the guys who started
the space race and when these americans
and the russians acquired these german
scientists this they poured a lot of
money into becoming the first to go to
space the russians were able to do it
first and then the americans were scared
what if they could new cars from space
what if they can drop nuclear bombs from
space so this space started like that at
that time the technology was not very
well developed and yet they were able to
do so much today you have enormous
advances in computing power you have
enormous amounts in material advances in
material science you have much stronger
materials you have way more powerful
computers that
you could not imagine in the 1960s and
so on so today we are seeing the
witnessing the birth of the second space
race it is more like a private space you
have your private companies that are
participating in this and there are two
three things happening firstly
in the next five years you're gonna
witness the great moon rush
everybody's going to rush for the moon
india tried it but we failed with the
chandrayaan-2 we were supposed to land
that lander there
for some reason the lander did not land
properly it crashed yes let's not go
into why that happened but uh we tried
now we are sleeping we should have
immediately the next year send the
sunday to sender chandrayaan three but
we still haven't done that
now sir the americans are planning to
launch this year
this year this year okay i see so the
americans are planning to send people to
the moon in 24 25 there abouts the
russians may be planning something the
chinese have been doing very good
progress in this
india is still sleeping
yes sir
russia and china have already signed a
memorandum of understanding
you are very well informed i am very
impressed very very impressed
so they are doing very well in this and
uh india is planning some things like
you said chandrayaan three this year
hopefully i hope and then we have this
manned space program crude space flight
which may happen gaganyan whatever they
call it so india will do something on
the other and so on right so the reason
why everybody is going to the moon right
now is because the moon is full of
resources first of all there is water
there in certain places that you can use
for a permanent moon station human
moon base there and also the regolith or
the soil that the
the soil of the moon it contains helium
10 etc or some things
it can be used yes sir
helium-3
ah helium-3 right i forget my physics
man
so that could be the fuel for future
nuclear reactors right uh fusion
reactors if we can build those yes so
once once we acquire that we are able to
develop the technology that the nuclear
fuel will be very very very valuable so
the moon is a great great place to get
that from so there are reasons why we
are first going for the moon there's
going to be a big rush for the moon in
the next 5 10 years i hope india is part
of that so that is what the space race
is about of course we know that elon
musk wants to go to the moon in the next
five 10 20 years maximum
and once that is
once we are able to do that other
countries will try and
uh
do the same thing emulate that so
eventually you will see a competition
for territory on the on on the moon and
on mars as well in the next 10 20 50 100
years so that's how one could expect
this to progress
sir and i have three
i have three suggestions for you
uh first of all
first of all it would be very cool if
you
bring a virologist to your podcast or an
astrobiologist
or other than that other than that
if you could bring someone with a
conflict of interest i mean who thinks
uh in a other way like uh some leftist
or something like that
no no no
no like like some leftist kind of guy so
give me a give me a name whom should i
bring it home should i bring in tell me
um
i don't know the names of any prominent
virologist or astrobiologist but i'm
talking about leftist give me the name
of a prominent leftist
mr
uh i don't know
like some journalist you know like okay
okay what's next
akash with energy i guess
don't hurt of him but okay
okay is that it
yes thank you sir all right nice meeting
you very interesting questions thank you
yes
take care bye
okay um
is there somebody who i have not met
before please raise your hands
okay uh rudra singh hello
hello namaste
namaste
nice to meet you nice to meet you what's
your question sir
sir from last step few days back of
singapore pm
um
absurd statement about india that
half of the mps in the parliament are
criminals
and
he he got this information from
international media
and
the thing is that
from
past two years or so
the entire propaganda is going from
western media that uh hindu phobic
propaganda that india is bad and this
and that
and
you can see
that um
from this propaganda our allies are also
having a negative sense about india
which they were not having few years
back or past decade or so this kind of
propaganda
and uh what can india do to tackle this
propaganda and
okay so you started with singapore okay
so let me address the singapore thing
the prime minister of singapore mr i
forget his name um i don't want to
mispronounce it so i'll not say it but
the prime minister he made some
statements about some
parliamentarians in india who have some
criminal record or something and he also
said something very nice about mr shree
shri javaral nehru and so on so i would
like to point out a couple of things
singapore is not a democracy it's a de
facto one party dictatorship
and the current prime minister of
singapore his father mr lee kuan yew was
the founder of singapore so to say and
he was an out and out dictator
he was a dictator
and he disappeared many people
who were not very convenient for him you
know disappearing someone one wonders
what that means
so who are these people to talk about
india they are not even a democracy
they are a dictatorship it's a one-party
dictatorship who are there to talk about
india
if they want to talk about india then
they should be prepared for the kind of
response that will come back
so we don't have to give
give a damn about what these people have
to say if they want to say something we
can show them the mirror first look at
yourself in the face look at the look at
yourself in the mirror then you talk
about somebody else now when you talk
about this
propaganda that is uh promoted in the
west this hindu phobic propaganda and
all there's nothing we can do about it
right because the entire western media
it serves their national interest it
serves the western interest we think
they have a free and fair media it's
it's it's an illusion the media over
there is nothing but the propaganda arm
of the state
the bbc is the propaganda arm of the of
the british government for the past god
knows how many decades that's what it is
it is simply propaganda we think that
because they have this posh english
accent that's what they they're right no
they are propagandists similarly for the
washington post new york times cnn
whatever else it is it's all propaganda
the thing we can do is once we have
sufficient money we can try and buy some
of those media outlets and then have
them tout or you know spout our
propaganda and what the other thing we
can do is why can't we have a bbc like
organization or cnn like organization of
our own which is globally relevant and
globally visible we have the money to do
it but apparently we don't have the will
to do it we have something called
doordarshan which is not even visible
within india it is still behaving like
it is in the 1970s so we need to
welcome ourselves into the 21st century
and play by the 21st century rule book
you know that's what we need to do
so that's what i can say sir nice
question good question thank you sir
and once again
meeting you thank you
sir you were making this small clip
videos previously
you were awesome please continue that
because it
engages the audience means
um not all the audience are here for
one or two
hour long podcast and these small gifts
at least it will grow your audience and
more people will come to see this
i hear you i hear you thank you for the
suggestion thank you
take care
namaskar namaskar take care bye
okay
uh i know people are waiting for quite
some time i apologize to everybody who's
waiting let's bring in mr prab johan
hello good morning sir
good morning sir where are you where are
you from winnipeg canada originally from
nice to meet you sir nice to meet you
so what's your question sir so my
question is
um
so it's a very sensitive topic and i've
been searching about it since when i was
a teenager but nobody could answer it
properly it's about operation bluestar v
punjab the people of the punjab have
been affected very very very extremely
by that operation
so i have couple of questions regarding
to that i am a very just to make clear
i'm not a
pro khalifani or something i have to
give the disclaimer i'm a very neutral
and fact-based person so my question is
couple of questions with regards to that
if i may ask
oh i could yeah
first of all
was it necessary
was the burning
was burning of the library sex reference
library
was which held many many historical
documents and literature literary facts
of the sikh history was it required to
burn it
and if the purpose was to flesh out the
kharkus
that could have been happened when they
were traveling india carrying ak-47s in
open in in an open environment
and the d was chosen of the day was
chosen when the founder of the golden
temple
was
um was
assassinated killed or eliminated by the
mughals that week was chosen
can
can we see it as a systematic killing of
a certain community by indian government
i
see i this is one chapter of history
that i am not very conversant with i i
can certainly say from a big picture
perspective
that the government the congress
government of that time messed this
situation up very badly
this could have been handled much better
whatever happened the the uh taking up
of arms and all that in this region that
could have been nipped in the bud it's
not like it they could not see it coming
so i think it was
botched up very badly that's that's what
i can say from a macro big picture
perspective i have not studied
the step-by-step uh
events of operation blue star what
happened what was burned what i know was
that there was a lot of destruction
uh was it needed was it required was it
necessary i don't quite know
uh maybe i will look into this in the
future and perhaps talk about this but
uh
from a very honest
perspective i don't quite know what
exactly happened there you know so
unfortunately i cannot answer that
question
if
go ahead go ahead let's let's yeah
so i am i am rajput
but i follow sikhism there's a quite a
debate between me and my friends that
how can i guess i can be a rajput so can
you please explain that
why can't you be a freaking rajput
yes please can you explain that to your
masters
see it's very simple it's very simple
see rajput is not a religion it is not a
belief system it's an ethnicity it's
your lineage that goes back a few
thousand years
so you could be
i mean there are lots of punjabi who are
converting to christianity today they
may be judged there will be rajputs
they're converting to christianity
i mean should they do that being rajputs
or juts
so so the thing is very simple whether
if you're a rajput it means that is your
lineage it means you have a certain line
of ancestry but it doesn't prevent you
from practicing whatever faith whatever
belief system whatever rituals
traditions you want it's your choice
so why can't you be a sick if you're a
rajput i see absolutely no nothing wrong
with that right that's all i can say
thank you lord sir and please keep
keep up this good work thank you
most welcome nice to meet you
okay um
okay let's bring in mr pranav roy
hello
so uh my question is
like a lot of people talk about akhan
bharat and uh even or somebody asked
question about that
if situation comes
should india emerge pakistan
but what we will get by uh remerging our
country with one of the most radical and
uh
useless kind of society
one question good question
good question it's always see before you
do anything you have to do a cost versus
benefit analysis
what is it going to cost you to do this
and what benefit do you gain from that
in the present situation in the present
context let's say it becomes possible
tomorrow to reintegrate pakistan should
we do it no
no not tomorrow not tomorrow not next
week not next year not next decade
the pakistani culture is incompatible
with indian values
but whether you like it or not that's
just the way it is they have this
culture of suicide bombing they have the
culture of terrorism they have the
culture of army rule and so on and so
forth right of all kinds of atrocities
you simply cannot have a population like
that and
allow them to
to run rampant in the rest of india you
simply cannot allow that
what india so so what needs to happen
this is our this is our land it is our
ancestral land no matter where you're
from whether you're from the east of
india partly but or anywhere else your
ancestors at some point in time lived in
that part of the of our country it is
the ancestral territory of all of us so
what needs to happen is first of all we
need to end this army rule
which means that for
in the next decade or so we have to end
the army rule we have to liberate the
people of sindh from that the people of
balochistan from that the people of
punjab people of pashtun
let them reintegrate or go independent
uh bring back pok at least
and then over time over a few decades we
can de-radicalize the people
de-traumatize the people and when
they're at a more civilized state of
existence we can reintegrate them so
it's not a next week project or next
month project it's a 100-year project
we are a very ancient civilization we
have to see things from a century upon
century perspective and we are simply
one of the links in the chain our
descendants will take care of that when
the time is right that's how we have to
see it
why do do you think that the indian
government is thinking like that
i think that this indian government now
is thinking differently from what we the
kind of governments we had in the past i
think there is a significant element of
long-term thinking now which is good all
right
all
one question and you have to answer like
yes no or i don't want to answer that
all right
good uh you keep talking about uh you
you keep talking about the uh that
invisible hand
that uh the in like in front of them the
indian government is like very weak uh
like uh
that invisible hand is
essentially united states and its allies
with the western world so-called western
world and some elements of the custom
it's possible
okay okay thank you all right thanks
thank you bye
uh
let's bring in mr rahul kadam i believe
i have not seen this gentleman before
hello sir how are you hello sir
sir where are you from
nice to meet you sir nice to meet you
what's your question
i have a question regarding
the uh
as you know that today is chatrabadi
shivaji maharaja
and i want to know how we are following
today the governance pattern which was
uh which were
followed by uh maratha empire during
their
uh
yeah their years of governance
are we are following that same pattern
or there is any difference in that
excellent question i spoke about this
briefly at the beginning of today's
session
so the pattern of governance and
administration that the maratha empire
had it is not being followed today in
india
okay it is not being followed at all the
principles and values of satrapata
shivaji have been consigned to the dust
bin today we are not
governing and administering this country
according to the vision the principles
and the values of shattered shivaji
maharaja we are not doing that
we raise slogans everyday
and all that we keep saying that it is
just slogans
though minutes logan boldly and bulger
that's
was a man of principles he had certain
values that he lived his life by and he
died by that
he was a great man and we are not
following those principles if he were to
see india today he would be deeply
disappointed with what our leaders have
done to this country this is not the
india he wanted he had a vision for
india
it was established for some time under
hinduism because of
because of his successors but then they
fitted it away and today's india is not
the india that chatrapati shivaji
maharaj wanted he would be deeply
disappointed to see this
so we are not following the governance
patterns the governance
system etc administration
and all that those principles of the
barata empire we are not we are totally
different from that we are following a
broken down western model
of of governance so that's that's why
india is not doing well today
so should we follow that or the two days
no
we have to see we have to do we have to
ask ourselves one question that in the
past 2000 years of our history
at what points in time was india great
and then we can ask ourselves
what about following that pattern and
adapting it for the 21st century
it's possible
see the principles of governance the
principles of power are timeless you can
always adapt them for any any situation
for any century so today we have the
21st century we can adapt those indian
principles
indian values for the 21st century and
that will be the right way to govern
india but that's not being done we are
blindly copying the west because we
think the west is better no it's not
better
so it's a very good question you've
asked a very very pertinent yes
one more question uh in today's
geopolitical situation means i am not
clear about
india whether india is pro russia or pro
us means india india
india is pro india you can only be pro
yourself in geopolitics there are no
permanent friends there are no permanent
enemies
if somebody's national interest aligns
with your national interest right now
you can cope cooperate with them
tomorrow their national interests may
change and then
you don't need to cooperate with them so
today india and russia are not as close
as they used to be 30 years ago but we
are not enemies we still have a great
amount of cooperation and we have a
common enemy china today russia and
china seem to be cooperating but in the
long run they are big enemies
so india and russia in the long run our
interests will converge
but
as you are aware that means china and
russia
both are following some type of
communism uh
so
we are
if we are pro russia then should
uh then uh
if the crisis comes whether russia will
support us or china what do you think or
it will be according to that division
if there is a crisis russia will do
whatever is best for their national
interest if supporting india is good for
the national interest they will do it if
supporting china is good they will do
that otherwise they will stay neutral
also there is also the option that's how
it goes so thank you and oh one advice
or maybe
just do long podcast uh about history
uh about any history i just love i just
watch your podcast about maratha empire
hp and i love you thank you sir
thank you so much thank you nice meeting
you tonight with you
okay um
whom shall i bring in let's bring in um
mr kebat
hello
namaskar sir where are you from
i'm from mumbai
yes sir nice to meet you what's your
question
wonderful to meet you sir as always
so uh sir once you mentioned
uh that the central asians
of today that
the people that occupy
central asia today are not the original
inhabitants of that region and they are
formed by mixing
and the merging of various other
populations
throughout the years
so could you throw some light on
the history of central asia
right the history of indonesia thousands
of years but what i can tell you tell
you in brief is this
for a great part of history central asia
was known as skitia
so the people who lived there were
nomadic people of indo-iranian origin
they were of indian origin actually if
you look at their genetics
you will know that they had dark hair
brown eyes and light brown skin so they
would look like me or many indians right
so that was the skit ethnicity uh they
also
re uh joined with india at a later time
so that was the ethnicity in central
asia for thousands of years and the
kusan's where you could call them the
easternmost kitchens right that's what
it was
then what happened was that there was
this uh
there was this new ethnicity that
emerged from the east from us from the
easternmost part of central asia which
was the
ethnicity of the ethnicity gave rise to
two peoples which is the mongols and the
turks
right so their culture religion was
thingism it's called tangirism nowadays
it was a polytheistic culture so the
mongols stayed in what is now mongolia
and the turks they spread throughout
various parts of central asia and when
they came in contact with islam and they
they absorbed islam that's the that's
when they became a militarily
expansionist and they conquered
porsche they conquered they started
trying to invade northern india and
after several centuries they were able
to make inroads and the so-called mughal
empire is of course a turkic empire
right they were they were talks so
that's what happened and when they were
able to uh spread across central asia
from a military perspective they did all
kinds of horrific atrocities that killed
lots of people and they took their women
as their slaves and that's how you have
this mixed population in central asia
today who look half turks and half
indian or iranian like the turkmens the
kazakhs etc there are various levels of
mixing the uighurs also the tajiks are
mainly still indo-iranian but apart from
that everybody else is mixed so that is
in a nutshell
what happened
so the same thing happened with turkey
as well right the turks migrated but
turkey is a whole different story
the people of turkey if you look at them
they are 99 anatolian or
or eastern european
there's very little actual turkic
central asian ethnicity in them some of
them you can see it's there but mostly
it is uh it is the local anatolia
anatolian
uh ethnicity and genetics that you will
find in these people in turkey and sir
uh what relation like what history do
the turks have with the tibet region
none
nothing no nothing nothing of any
significance nothing substantial
nothing's absurd
um so uh all right so you got three
questions so that should be enough
all right thank you
nice to
hello
good evening sir
good evening alokji where are you from
nice meeting you sir what's your
question
sir actually i want to ask a question
from joe paul dixon
sure
okay so during cold war in 1962 the u.s
and russia or ussr to be exact they got
engaged in veritas situation in cuba
popularly known as cuban missile crisis
so
around the same time the people's
republic of china they decided to attack
india along the mcmohan line sir so
drawing its panel with the current
geopolitical scenario
where again
us and russia are engaged confronting
each other
in ukraine so
can we say that can it be a possibility
that china can invade
taiwan as we are seeing that every other
day the people celebration army and
specifically their air force are
violating the taiwanese airspace and
also conducting various military trades
there so can it be a possibility that
china can invade taiwan under the shadow
of this ukraine crisis
very very good question yes it's all a
possibility so in india we talk about a
two-front war right we talk about the
specter of a two-front war one from the
chinese side one from the pakistani side
so there is the specter of a much larger
two-front scenario one in ukraine one in
taiwan so right now the western media is
tom tomming the possibility that mr
putin may order the invasion of ukraine
tomorrow or today evening or whatever
it's apparently imminent it could happen
anytime and then in the next couple of
days that's what they are saying no i
don't know how true that is that i mean
i don't think anybody has any access to
the inner thinking in the workings of mr
putin's mind but
but let's say
that the russians were to invade ukraine
the nato people the americans would want
to try and prevent that which means that
they would get involved there in some
military action that would be the
perfect opportunity for mr xi jinping to
use that distraction as the opportunity
to make a move on taiwan it is
it makes sense from a military and
geopolitical perspective
so i think if one thing were to happen
there is a possibility that the other
thing may also happen before time
because we know there is a certain
amount of cooperation in coordination
between russia and china the so-called
dragon bear scenario so yes it's a
possibility certainly it is
sir sir and i have a request also sir
sir in many of your indian history
podcast you have covered the history of
india mainly from the territorial
perspective so sir i want you to cover
the maritime perspective sir sir as i
have read books by sanjiv sanyasar
the land of seven rivers and indian
ocean children of people so i want you
to cover the history of india from
maritime perspectives as we have seen
that india has many
influences in south east asia especially
in indonesia and
myanmar thailand also so such that is a
request from me
very good i'm a big fan of your sir
thank you thank you so much nice meeting
you guys nice to meet you thank
you bye
okay who is sleeping shall i wake
somebody up let's bring in mr sia saran
hello
hi sir how are you
i am very well sir how are you doing
i'm from tokyo i was in your podcast uh
i think a couple of three or four days
back also
thank you thank you for giving me
another opportunity so my quick one
question is regarding the 1857
um
you know first war of independence
because
uh in our culture we have
been brainwashed to uh
to to
realize or to believe that we are not
one people we have all the kind of
differences
be it religious or you know social or
maybe caste system
but we saw worker was very pointed in
saying that no this was our first war of
independence
and even until in the modern times we
get that
uh
you know exposure to that concept but
nobody really delves on it that why it
was the first war of independence and
why it was very important to say it
as it was the first war of independence
against the britishers and we were one
people and even in today's
hijab road which is going on today
you know it is kind of giving it a uh
an excuse or a justification that yes it
was just a mutiny it was nothing
independence india was never one you
were all different so what's your take
on that
my take is very simple our historians
have done their utmost to portray this
as a rebellion as a revolt as a mutiny
like it's a it's a small little incident
it was actually a pan-india thing it
happened all across india spontaneously
at that time we did not have cell phones
we did not have internet and still
this entire uprising took place it was
no doubt a war of independence and how
do
on what basis do i say it's a war of
independence look at the death toll
more than 10 million indians died in
this in the aftermath of this it took a
long time for the british to suppress
all the various uh
geographical the spread of this thing
and in the aftermath of this entire uh
war more than 10 million indians died i
don't have the reference right now but
if you look it up even from the british
perspective i think it was published in
the guardian or something and there's
been a book written about this that the
british killed at least 10 million
indians
in the aftermath of this war when 10
million million people die it's not a
mutiny
it's not a rebellion it's a war and it's
a subcontinent-sized war so that itself
should tell everybody it's a war but our
historians have never highlighted the
fact that more than 10 million indians
were killed by the british in the
aftermath of this uh of this war so we
all think it's a mutiny it's a chota
mother happening one mangal pandey did
something one tatiato did something one
rani of lakshmi died and that's it it's
not like that it spread all across the
subcontinent
not everywhere as always the british
were able to use their policy of divide
and rule they kept some people
who they were able to induce some people
in some parts of india to fight on their
behalf and eventually that's how they
were able to prevail
so they have always been good at uh
exploiting whatever divisions
existed in indian society and
enhancing those divisions and that's a
policy that has been followed
since 1947 also our historians everybody
academics politicians
all they have done is to try and divide
us further and that's why today indians
don't really see themselves as one
people
i mean our
local sub-national identity
it takes precedence over the national
identity because we don't have a single
uh unifying civilization language except
english which is a foreign language
we the the role of sanskrit has been
totally removed so we don't have a
unified identity anymore and the
government has ensured it is not there
so there are reasons why we are so
disunited even today
but i think because of the internet we
can all start realizing that we are just
one people if you go back
a couple of thousand years we all have
the same ancestors
so that's what i can say from
perspective thank you nice meeting you
thank you youtube cheers
okay let's uh
whom shall i bring in i can see people
waiting
uh let's bring in mr ratan
hello
uh hi sir how are you
i am very well sir where are you from
uh i'm from bihar uh first of all i was
not able to complete my education due to
some financial crisis but still i have a
great interest in politics and all so i
have a three question uh as someone
asked earlier that like as the russian
ukraine war is going on so china might
invade taiwan so uh
continuing that same question do we have
opportunity to like uh get the poke back
like if russia tried to invade ukraine
and on the same time if china want to
like invade taiwan because they both are
allies today china and russia right so
can india like uh tackle pakistan and
get the poke back because we have our
highest military and uh
this air force and nav naval force
everything we have okay so this is the
first question second uh that between
the time of
nine let's take one question let's take
one question one i think it's a very
good question that you asked so let me
take that one
so what i would say is that when it when
it comes to nuclear weapons state
whether states whether we like it or not
the pakistanis have nuclear weapons
and we should have see
from our perspective we should have a
very clear understanding of where the
pakistani military's red line lies
so what is a nuclear redline it is the
threshold beyond which they will be
compelled to use nuclear weapons
we don't ever want to cross that
threshold whether it is with pakistan or
with china right
so we
from our strategic perspective we need
to have very clear understanding of what
the red line is i am not sure pok is a
red line for them but if you were to try
and go further it may be a red line what
i would say is this
if
the chinese make a move on taiwan if
they attempt an invasion of taiwan
india should at the moment not think
about pok india should immediately
secure nepal and sri lanka that's what i
would say
there is no nuclear redline there
so that's what india should do
what is
easier to
obtain we should obtain that i'm not
saying it should invite invade and
occupy it i am saying we should secure
let's call it secure we should secure
nepal and sri lanka if the chinese dare
to invade taiwan we should immediately
do that
poke will think about later so that's
what i would say but of course i am not
running the government so it's just a
suggestion
right okay
okay uh one more question so please so
between the time of 1990 and 1960 uh we
have a currency of like five thousand
thousand and ten thousand rupees okay i
don't know much about it so can you
please give more details on that like
how india demonetized like in the
british uh like time between 1957 uh
before 1947 and after like 1947 i think
pandit
continued the same thing like he
continued everything we all know that no
i don't i don't know
all the way
i don't have sufficient information
about that i have not studied the
uh monetary history and
all that of india so i won't be able to
answer this sorry
okay
thank you so much sir thank you nice
meeting you nice to meet you
thank you so much
uh let's take hopefully one or two more
questions i know lots of people are
waiting utkarsh
hello hello
hello where are you from have you met
before
yes sir last podcast i met
if i'm from
uh shanghai hello oh yes yes yes my
friend from what's up sir how are you
doing
hi good sir
everybody i must be some agent or
something i'm not an agent i'm very
patriotic person well i never said that
there was some people going down in the
comments
okay okay what's your question sir
okay so i want to ask uh
for a very long time us indians we are
stuck in this bubble of vasudeva become
we are not we are peaceful people we are
like this we are like that we should not
be expansionist so how can somebody even
maintain their power on a global stature
on a global stage basically how can we
maintain our status our stature if we
are not expansionist be it china be the
united states be it russia russia has
its own sphere of influence china is
trying to build its own being
expansionist and all japan when they had
the power they went deep inside china
all over asia even in myanmar even until
nagaland they reached right uss has its
own sphere of influence if india if we
just maintain this kind of bad attitude
that we are not expansionist or we we
are so peace loving people how can we
even even just even if we do become
superpower how will we sustain that for
the long run and so extension of this
why don't we just take p okay like just
be assertive about it we just take it we
just finish this problem let's just
separate pakistan and china they are
neighbors because of that right that's
why china keeps poking us okay i'm
sitting here but still they keep poking
us through pakistan because they have a
boundary if they just they are just not
connected they have to deal with us
your comments sir
yeah good question so i think we should
learn from your hosts china i mean the
chinese are very assertive they are
always expansionist they have
territorial disputes with all their
neighbors
certain territorial disputes are
currently dormant but they will be
reopened at the appropriate time so they
have territorial designs on everybody
and this attitude of vasudeva cotton
become it comes from the
line of thinking of shri mohandas gandhi
and shari nehru and so on which wants to
lull indians into being the passive
non-aggressive and all that
so
india has always been history india has
always historically had a very large
sphere of influence it's been cultural
mostly and
uh it's been trade related also but from
time to time india has also been an
expansionist powered under certain
emperors from time to time so if india
wants to secure its position as a
geopolitical power
securing at least in this indian
subcontinent then it needs to have a
military sphere of influence that
extends way beyond its borders that is
non-negotiable it has to happen
otherwise india is not even regional
power
so like you said we will have to deal
with the pok situation sooner or later
right now there is a nuclear threshold
so we need to calculate exactly what is
the pakistan army's nuclear threshold
the nuclear red line and if pok is not
part of that we should go ahead and do
it so it is something that you cannot do
it
you cannot take it flippantly it is a
very serious question
anytime you go to war there has to be a
proper amount of calculation that goes
behind that the
uh all the cost benefit analysis the
scenarios that can you'd war game the
entire situation so i think that india
needs to find the opportunity in the
next few years to take back pure no
doubt about it and if we do that then we
can cut off china from its access to
pakistan so all this needs to happen as
india grows economically it will also
grow militarily in proportion and when
the time is right
and soon i would say in the next five to
ten years maximum we need to
uh secure pok for sure so yeah i agree
with the thing you said
so uh do you think pakistan even has a
nuclear threshold so they are puny
little country you know that compared to
the size of india even if let's say that
they're like pakistan will cease to
exist i don't think they'll be so stupid
to you know start a nuclear war in india
they always say that new tactical
nuclear weapons nuclear weapons can't be
tactical once you drop even a tactical
nuclear weapons on india you just cannot
control the repercussions of it india
will just
india will have to go at it so do you
think that so we don't want to
so we don't want to inherit
a nuclear wasteland
i know i agree that if the pakistan is
there to take us use a single nuke
against against us we're going to
flatten them for sure
but then what are the what is the
consequence of that we're going to
inherit a nuclear wasteland do we want
our ancestral lands to be polluted by
nuclear
pollution for centuries we don't want
that
we have to think long term it's not
about what happens now
it's about where do we want to go in the
next 100 200 years a leader has to think
that way from our perspective we can
think abhi karlo let's do it but then
what happens
there's going to be nuclear fallout that
will spread all across the indian
subcontinent it will spread across india
also if there is a nuclear war so we
don't want to cross the nuclear
threshold the best way of fighting
the supreme art of fighting is to
acquire what you want without firing a
single shot
that's yeah
that's how we have to do it
so that's the ideal way of fighting when
the
when your people don't even realize that
you've won a big victory it looks so
effortless that's actually what needs to
happen so let's see how it goes but we
need to take back be okay sooner rather
than later
right thank you
thank you so much thank you nice meeting
you nice meeting you thank you
okay let me take one final question
let's bring in mr abhishek hello hello
there
hi nice meeting you where are you from
west bengal yes great what's your
question
sir can you tell me about who was bhapa
raval i hear a lot about him but we
don't know much about him
answer my uh one guy another question is
that who was the greatest leader in
indian history
okay okay um
greatest leader in indian history look
india has a 10 000 plus year old history
so it's almost impossible to pinpoint
one person there is the great king
bharat after whom our land is named
so there is one we have lord ram lord
krishna great leaders incredibly great
leaders we still worship them as gods so
there we can i can give those two
examples we have kanishka the great we
have the great mauryan leader uh
chandragupta maurya we had multiple
great gupta
emperors like kumar gupta chandragupta
and um
[Music]
samudragupta etc uh we had uh
who else did we have
the peeta then we had the great chula
emperors rajendra chola rajarat chola
then we of course had the great shivaji
maharaja
maharaja so we had so many great leaders
it's impossible to pinpoint one now
what's the other question you asked i it
went out of my mind
[Music]
yes sir
so baba rawal was
um
you will find very little written about
him in textbooks in history books
he was a rod booth warrior
and
he was a he was a very
successful and powerful warrior
uh
i think his greatest accomplishment was
in defeating the turks who had taken
over parts of western india and
repulsing them significant distance back
westwards and he was able to reconquer
punjab get rid of the turks and
establish uh civilization again for some
time there and he even founded the city
which is now called rawalpindi
and i believe it is said according to
the legend or the story that he was a
disciple of baba guru gura khanat
and when he retired from his career as a
warrior he went up north
and
he and his warriors went up north and
they married among the people of the
himalayan foothills and their
descendants are called the gorkhas so
they're great warriors right because
they have this rajput tradition in the
world tradition
so that is supposed supposed to be the
origin of the gorkha people of present
in northern india nepal etc so that's
what i can say in brief about
great warrior
sosa means gurkhas are also a lineage of
rajput
certainly yes yes
answer another question one question
uh sir
yes everyone
so why didn't india annexed bangladesh
in 1971 why they it was i think
we will have to we will have to reinvoke
i don't know i don't have an answer
maybe the americans and the soviets
did not allow us maybe they aren't to
set the indian government maybe the
great indian government of the time was
not that powerful as we imagine it to be
we won this victory we had the right of
conquest we conquered east pakistan it
was hours by right of conquest it was
our territory anyway thousands of years
and yet we did not
reintegrate it so i don't have an answer
i simply don't understand why we didn't
we did not do it
but yeah it's a valid question very good
question
all right sir
uh thank you sir
nice sir thank you nice to meet you
thank you
all right i think we are at the end of
today's session i apologize to the
people who are waiting i know lots of
people are waiting
should i bring in one more person
one more person okay one last person
i'll bring in mr manmoth
tiwari hello hello sir nice to meet you
again sir
yeah actually i'm preparing for my jeep
so i don't get a lot of time
where are you from again i forgot
i am from lucknow
okay let's uh so yours is the last
question for today what is the question
i'll be very grateful for that i want to
ask that
how to completely decolonize my mind
like despite knowing the fact how great
and scientifically advanced my
civilization work
still some sort of hesitation is still
left in me on like some sort of
hesitating hesitation that is stopping
from wearing my cultural identity on my
sleeves like even i think some
some part of my mind still think that
speaking in english is like
intellectually more superior than
speaking in india how do i deal with it
in fact like rather than in fact i know
that
english is an inferior language but
still there is some sort of
uh inferiority complex complexion
in the subconscious mind how to deal
with it yeah yeah good question uh the
first thing you have to realize is that
it is not your fault that you feel this
way
since the time you were born this has
been drilled into your head from lots of
different places your teachers the
education system the medium of education
the media the movies everybody all the
so-called influencers they put this into
our heads it takes a lot of time for
this to this process to be undone the
first thing is that since
the fact that you realize that you when
you
to some extent mentally colonized that
itself is a big victory
right so now what you have to do is you
have to find ways to reconnect with our
ancient culture maybe you could try and
learn something maybe you can try and
look at various other things
it's a long process uh it cannot happen
tomorrow next week maybe you should give
yourself five to ten years and maybe
that
it's a process of growth growing as a
person
we grow over years decades
it's not going to happen tomorrow even i
am mentally equivalent to an extent i'm
speaking english i'm more comfortable
with english whether i like it or not
it's just what i have gone through in my
life and i am this is the outcome of
that
but as long as you realize
that you know english is not a superior
language and our culture was once very
great it is still the superior culture
and then when we try to reconnect with
it in various ways that's how you grow
you evolve and you decolonize it's a
long process
so one last things one suggestion i want
to take from you sir so like like in
your previous videos you keep saying
that iips of india are not up to their
standards and like yeah some in some way
like not good enough but then that stars
that demotivates me from preparing for
my day
see
it doesn't matter where you go what
matters is what quality lies inside you
you may go to the worst school worst
college in the world but as long as you
have a certain quality and you are and
you when you develop yourself
sufficiently then it doesn't matter what
school college you go to
and the iits are not that bad they are
they are worse than what i would want
them to be i want the iits to be the
best institution in the world that is
the standards i have and from that
standard from that perspective i find
them disappointing that doesn't mean
they are bad that doesn't mean they're
terrible they can be better
but they can serve the purpose for most
indian students as long as you take the
time to develop yourself into us into a
superior human being but you can it's
all up to you it's your choice what you
do and you have the strength in you to
do it so don't feel demotivated by my
criticism of the iits the criticism is
valid but it doesn't mean that the
incidents are that bad they are still
reasonably okay
it what really matters is how
you
uh
approach your life you can make the best
of any situation so that's what i would
say don't be demotivated
thank you thank you so much a big fan
thank you so much nice meeting you
bye
okay gentlemen and ladies ladies and
gentlemen gentlemen's gentlemens all
right
uh that brings us to the end of today's
session i apologize to my friends who
are waiting really sorry
uh
so tomorrow we will have one more
session just like this
and the ones who came in today
hopefully i will not bring them again
tomorrow and i'll bring in i will give
opportunities to newer people tomorrow
so i apologize to those who are waiting
please come again tomorrow i will give i
will try and give the chance to as many
of you as possible
i will see you tomorrow see you tomorrow
until that time take care
thank you everybody for watching for
your support and i'll see you tomorrow
thank you bye